V
Um
So don't forg that
Now on to a new
category fourth
category and I
described it to you
briefly in a very
General way
yesterday and
remember that We're
talking about a
conclusion or an
outcome of a
transaction or an
exchange so uh the
conclusion here the
outcome of the
transaction is that
we decided that the
first two times that
the budd tau the
first two turnings
of the wheel are to be
taken AS
figurative that he
didn't mean what He
said He was for the
sake of the students
He was adjusting
what He said and
then the third
turning of the wheel
the third Major
period of his
teachings during
that time he did
mean what He said
because during that
time he explained
that he didn't mean
what He said the
first two turnings
of the wheel uh and
then uh ges Goes On
to
say That's the
meaning of is a
conclusion
transaction sorry
the result of
exchange that has
happened the B has
asked the budha A
Question and the
budha has answered
the B and in the
exchange as an
outcome of the
exchange the B
asking the buddha
question and the
buddha answering the
B We have come  to
this realization of
what it of what it
means to to what the
first two turnings
of the wheel were
And what the last
tur of the wheel were
and that has that meaning then has been has come out dr from From from come here the first is for act and second will be and uh
of the
wheel is is literal
so You're going to
get Now uh very uh
laid out clearly
each all the details
of of the what we
Call the outcome or
the result of the
transaction are
going to be laid out
here those that
Which we only
described very
briefly so far
there
thec what just
explained but Now
You're going to get
he's going to go
through each of
theel and explain
the details of what
he meant and why
They are literal or
why They are
f
or
h or
the next section is
don't forget the
original question of
the  B the B came to
Lord  buddha and said
you know in the
first section or the
first first section
of teachings you
gave and then in
certain sections of
teachings you gave
You said that
everything existed
by definition
meaning referring to
the first tur of the
wheel and then later
You said that
nothing exed by def
and remember was
what you mean You
said that you know
what were you trying
to accomplish was
your true intention
When You said those
things and now in
reply or as an
outcome of the
transaction right
We're going to find
out Lord buddha is
going to go through
again We're
not so much talking
about the different
subjects of the
turnings of the
wheel but rather
whether or not when
He said that these
categories exist by
definition or these
categories Don't
exist by defin the
main not so much the
meaning each the
categories Spoke
about remember in
the first
he Spoke many
categories of
existing things from
physical body All
the Way Up to the 37
compon of
enlightenment So
it's not so much the
question of what did
he mean when he tght
those the question
is what did he mean
when He said all of
those things do
exist by  definition
and then when he got
to the  first of the
wheel
I
said exed by
definition and the
content ofd
by definition and
part of those things
I said Don't EX by
definition do EX by
definition So that
be the content of
the third theel and
that will be what
call
outcome
for If You look upon
the turnings of
theel AS we talked
about them so
far there should be
parts of them which
are extremely clear
extremely defined
extremely you know
well well defined
You know You
can clearly decide
One thing or the
other about them you
know some some of
them Like That
and some of them are
not so well defined
yet  There's still
some kind of debate
about them
or them  If you take
those theel guys a
cons them consat
them into things
that clearly well
defined stated cut
and dried and then
things which are still kind of fuzzy and not decided yet and not not determined yet in the three turns
two
you
made and simar
to
matter
matter andic status
of the subject
matter and in a way
That's the thing
getting into the
meaning Can You just
divide it AS spe of
the budha into two
categories what you
said Is You said is
and said is true but
That's not That's
not the Dire I want
to go
in
think
number
unle
there
but
yes
you to the midle
school touch nobody
Rush there just up a
little We're
cracking the door
open and We're
taking out of that
room the concept
called that  Those
sutras Which the
buddha Spoke Which
We are to take
literally and those
sutr Which the bud
Spoke Which We are
to take figuratively
Which we have to
interpret in order
to find out the real
meaning so says that
distinction is made
in the su which are
to be taken
literally and the su
Which were me fig
and we have a
corresponding
distinction made in
the mind sch the
same language is
used the budd spokes
certain su which are
literal the buddha
sp certain su which
are figurative so
there the same
expressions exist in
the middle way
school and in the
mind only school the
middle school says
some of what the bud
some of the su are
figurative some are
literal and then
when you get into
the scho also use
the same verbiage
right and
meanig and schol
says when they say
lal and figurative
are not the same you
have to realize that
there There's a
distinction or a
difference between
what the min school
says when they say
some suit are
figurative and some
suit are literal and
the middle way
school says when
they say some su are
figurative and some
suit are  literal so
We're going
difference they mean
lal and figura
su
um
m he want ele to
answer this Question
here how the answer
here's how the
question comes Okay
he says we take that
door and leave it
open a cra we won't
SH it all together
for the time being
let that door stay
Open the middle
school door leave it
open just a bit Now
says go back to the
schol got cat things
taken sorry
figuratively you got
this category of
things su or speech
of the budha which
is supposed to be
taken  figuratively
and there must be in
the mind only school
a measure of what it
is to be literal or
not literal so if
there must be a test
or litm test that
When you go to that
uh that speech of
the budha that
particular uh thing
that the buddha said
that you Can you can
judge it against
this measure to
decide whether or
not this is
figurative and then
there must be
separate You can use
you
and this is test
test against
deci thing Spoke
literal or not And
this is figurative
or not so there must
be these  two kinds
of  test to decide or
measures of what it
is to be figurative
or not figura what
do you think those
two tests are what do
you think a test
would
be
all tce so I'm
choosing you to tell
us What it is what
is the test the sch
US to decide
something is
lal
m
implicit
or
You can take
words
ands precisely so if
you can take the act
wording of the bud
said and follow it
exactly on face
value exactly
literally right exactly
according to
what the word say
every single word
then that becomes
what we call lal  and
then figurative
becomes those things
Which You cannot
Take on face val you
cann You can
understand the Words
in
discp the
Words
and that is figura
and
any the Words State
exactly what the me
you to understand
from Words then that is
that is lal and
in tibetan the
is Which means to
acc to the
ver
think about the
whole lal and
down means can
EX
AC AS being exactly
what the word says
and
so downes word
can
We are in the
mind section even
though It's not
something going to
be coming directly
from this section
because there's  a
deep relationship
between what the
middle school sorry
the mind only school
defines as being
figurative and
literal and There's
such a deep
connection between
that And what the
middle school says
is literal and
figurative I'm going
to insert here the
explanation of the
middle school the
different one of
what it is to be
literal and
figurative so Here
we go to the midle
schs
acc a very crucial
point in in midle
way school
any speech of the
buddha in Which Lord
budha talk directly
about
emptiness we won say
Spoke directly say
clearly Okay Any spe
of the buddha in
Which Lord budha
clearly referred to
emptiness that is
that is lal spe of
the buddha and Any
spe of the bud in
Which the bud did
not clearly refer to
spe
ID
right And you can
think he for EX Lord
made stat anything
produced
bya Changing and
eventually will die
so
That's all produce
things are
Changing and
impermanent so Lord
bud said that Now
according to the
mind sch idea of ​​the
distinction
andig  tak EX AS
Lord so
foral spe of the
buddha which is
literal but then
would it qualify AS
literal according to
the middle schools
explanation Of
literal No Because
it doesn't clearly
speak about
emptiness itself and
that therefore There
are parts There are
sections of what the
min school believes
literal that cannot
be taken literally
once you get to the
midd school because
they
again
so Now back go
back We're on page
26 We're on the last
line where
say and here says He
has by implication
or He has implicit
not explicit right
He has  BYC
come the
first figur and the
final is now is
he the so as
outcome the
transaction of the
exchange he
meaning has come to
a realization that
the first outcome of the exchange
where he realizes that
the first two the figurative and the last one was l um inet word forcit meaning not explic never been st that has never 먹 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹튀 먹 먹튀 먹 먹튀 먹 먹 먹 먹 sufficiently wood has come to a realization that the first outcome of the exchange where he reales that the first two
the figurative
and the
last one was l um inet word forcit meaning not
explic never been st that has neverly st I get first yet has the B come and said Oh I get it in that Sense
right all He said
was I get it right
so he didn't come
and say he didn't
come and say  outri
that Oh I get it
that the first two
turns of the world
were spoken
figuratively and the
last one was spoken
literally but by
implication
implicitly and in
tibetan the word for
implicitly is shuki
Which means by the
power of and then
ges says you know by
the power of means
Which means By The
Force of and kind of
thing where One
thing happens and
then another thing
we know has happened
so you've got the
electrical
generating station
back there uh is
generating power and
then on the basis of
that this FAN is
turning around over
Your Head Now and
and that's by the
power of the
electrical
generating station
then the then the
fan is going so uh
You can assume uh
He's implicitly
saying You can
assume that it FAN
is going the
electrical
generating station
must be going now
also and and that's
He's using a pun he
saying The Power Of
The Station is
running the
by
BYC implication We
can understand that
he under that He has
understood
the first two theel
are figurative and
that the
last that
hasn't
just
the
word
BYC I
says
turn  and he's going
to make some banging
and
st Okay into
distinction
between is the one
we have before Which
me By The Force of
something and being
through the force of
something so here we
have By The Force of
something meaning
you think about
there el
ener and takes time
elc to trav get the
the fan starts
moving so That would
be one kind of
implication Where
the mind perceives
One thing and then
that triggers a
subsequent
understanding in the
mind and that's
called by the power
something but then
There's another
expression tibetan
and Another Way of
understanding the
word Which Which
means Almost by the
way
in english means
incident means How
say con to something
So that means like
when understanding
that sound is not
something which is
permanent suppose
you come to
understanding that
sound is not
something which is
permanent then there
is a part of your
mind Which at the
same moment
simultaneously conc
is understanding
that S impermanent
me when there state
of
minded
conee you are Almost
by
implication
understanding that
sound is Changing
and those are Almost
con those are Almost
taing simultaneously
sotin between two
versions of the
phrase meaning by
the power of that
this occurs
lateran
timec
think
implication
figurative the
second theel was
something figurative
and the third theel
was something
literal but What's
happening Here is
that by implication
is thinking or
conceiving in terms
of three turnings of
the wheel and Now we
can Start to talk
about the three
stages of the
turnings of the
wheel or the three
Steps of the turning
of the wheel and
then we Start to get
into time or
Historical time
right that one occurs
Before The other and
then the next ur
you know they
SE or
Now we get in the
next se another
quotation from the
remember name in
Which the bud exps
the real thing he
had in mind he the
other
su So when we get
down there Now
the
how
EX in the sura how
he understand it how it is
that the
first fur and that
section begins with
the third l p 27 and
continues down to
the from the
btom
SP
me
help
him character the
spe of the bud in
saying figura these
are found onine
US
means unp
right This one
means
kinde that Which
does something
better
means it ISP There
is something lally
means there does EX
a  time What that
means get to lerd
one is me something
to be tak
and that
means something is
not
decided still
have point of
discussion How that
point of discussion
of further discussion
and those are the
four character
characterizations by
the about the first
theel in indicating
that was figurative
we through
says you know we g
through the meaning
of that already you
know actually You
and I have already g
through the meaning
of these
Words by their
intention and Now go
back And see if we
can straight
out them what are they
saying what is the
lal meaning these
words
me
Now There are When
you take these four
expressions which
are sort of unusual
right and Don't
Forget They are the
actual word of the
buddha right They
are part of the
sutra in Which the
buddha explains what
he meant in the sut
so we are We are
talking about the
word of an
enlightened being
right and then we
have people trying
to explain what
these four
expressions mean and
there have been two
great schools of
explanation one is
what you're going to
get from J uh in his
in this uh
text right here and
then  There's another
one Which we been
calling  the chin's
commentary Chinese
commentary And this
is a great Master
name in tibetan he
thinks he says I
think it's in in
tibetan and in
chinese but Anyway
this other Master
has a way of
explaining Which
slightly Don't
Forget when we go
through the on some
the four and other
will be saying the
but some the others
the will not be we
say that There are
two trad exp even
though some they do
age
Now Don't Forget
that get the point
Where is explaining
the wording of the
sura right first He
said I  will set
forth the wording of
sutra and then I
will explain the
wording the sutra so
We're not quite
ready to get to the
second part yet So
my suggestion is you
guys Leave a big
empty page here
after these four and
then we to come back
to that later
meaning of empty sp
in
under back and
exp Now if we Follow
the act order of
this particular book
right and the actual
order the sutra
rather than jumping
to the
explanation now now
that has expressed
why he thinks the
first turning of the
wheel is figurative
now he moves on to
express why  he feels
the second  turn of
the wheel was
something spoken
figuratively And
what does he use AS
his justification
for saying that the
theel sp the
characters the
There is there is a
point or there is a
time I believe that
one means there is a
point at Which you
have to take it
figura something you
see I mean there is
a point uh and then
uh It is figurative
and then there is a
point of discussion
here those four
characterizations uh
the B uses again in
the sutra at this
point again if we
Follow the act order
of this text so  far
we don't skip around
We are now in
ination
he he
You don't have to
leave you know a
million pages of
empty notebook there
you know just need a
little B Come back
to
that
You can take
allan them over you
know just make
Which means surp
becomes L Which
means
unsurpass can't be
out right and in
Which I believe
means there is a
chance to debate
about it becomes
means There is no
chance to debate
about it the meaning
of it right and then
TR Which means
figurative changes
in the Which means
literal and then
Which means still  a
point of discussion
becomes Which means
no longer a point of
discussion So when
he gets to the
first two
with
take
over
We have
take and split it up
Into The sep
countries There we
got the first the
wheel second the
wheel third we have
to draw our borders
our International
borders Now between
the
different theat so
back 27
You Go up S Lines
from the botom
There's aase
there with the
Words the first the
characterization or
the description of
the first the wheel
has been completed
So all the sutra
statement up there
refers to the first
the wheel go to page
28 and the first
line where It
says that is the end
of the second theel
that marks the
border of the end of
the second theel in
his description in
the bice description
then you skip down
to let's see 3 eight
Lines from the
bottom on page 28
you get the end of
the su quotation
Which
isce and that's
Where the third the
wheel is so just AS
we have to draw
International
borders between
india America Tibet
things Like That
here we have dra our
International
borders between the
first second third
wheels in this
quote because we
kind  have
in
umna page 28 uh the
sth line from the
bottom and here
becomes here begins
uh J explanation of
of the wording of
that sutra uh his
explanation will
come in in two parts
first is called a
brief a just a bit
explanation of what
the meaning of the
sutra is and then
secondly He'll say
just a bit on how we
draw the distinction
between What is
literal and what is
figurative so That's
take
inra has talking
about how he
believes that the
first Turn the wheel
and the second Turn
the wheel  are
figurative And how
he thinks that the
third the wheel is
literal He's already
gone through that
and
nowa in two sections
is going to explain
the sutra and then
explain just a bit
about the
distinction between
literal and
figurative and in
his ex  planation of
the of the
sutra
L Anyway the body
goes through each of
those three turnings
of the wheel And
explains what how he
feels It is then J
is going to go back
and and take Oh
That's what He said
he's going to go
back and rip apart
each word that of
the sutr so J is
going to go through
and say this is the
meaning of this
Words this is the
meaning of these
phrases This is what
he meant when He
said that so he to
do that And what
He's on to next so
he goes Back  to the
act word
me
um um me me um ah
okay nowd to down
jess down the
LOC this teaching
Where is this going
to happen you know
he talking about the
sutra and to NA down
where this is taking
place so he
says and that
means is the correct
pronation of the S
for IF YOU
they call in the
West And this is the
general local or the
general you could
say like area in
Which the buddha
gave this teaching
and then more
specifically If you
say the exact spot
where he gave the
teaching It's a
place called Trans
rak
transak  and riders
to rid means wild
animals like  dear
and st Like That
means forest so the
point of
saying is is to
indicate that the
buddha wanted to get
out of the City
where all noisy and
a lot of busy
commotion going on
and he wanted to go
out to a quiet place
we call in tibetan
means like a sort of
a uh out in the
middle of Nowhere
you know like some
kind of isolated
place and He wants
to go out there and
he's going to go out
there and he's going
to give this
teaching Now
nowadays we
identified that
particular quiet
place so outside
ofan in a place
where building
monies and st like
there some
tibetan you know
organ in place So
outs In the in the
place of the forest
of the wild animals
outside of varan did
the budd give this
teaching and Now
there a prefix
before that called
Trans Trans
means place of
the spe of the city
city meaning a great
something i i had to
translate it and I
didn't know how to
translate so I said
by the way how do we
translate how I was
supposed to explain
the wording
uh speech of the
which is attached to
the  speech of the of
the great master
speech of the great
yogi which is
attached to the
Words uh the wild
animal forest you
see and he says well
There's two
explanations of it
and i now i'm not
talking uh
scriptural authority
I'm talking oral
tradition you know
things I've heard
and I can't Really
attest
place Where the
Master Spoke place
The Great yog Spoke
right and the great
City so so he says
some people take AS
place where Lord
buddha Spoke the
teaching and that's
why called place of
the  spe of the City
but heard more
interesting
exp
fell and place the
City fell he says
means in planet
before Lord buddha
came down from To
Heaven where He was
living uh and
exhibited or
pretended to go
through the 12 great
deeds of a buddha
right like becoming
enlighten was a Play
he put it on right
so before Lord
buddha came down
from his Paradise
and exhibited the 12
activities of
enlightened being
there were on this
planet many people
who had already
achieved high
spiritual states
because of their
former lives so
there were for
example tong  songs
or cities in  the
Sense where City
refers to an AR
meaning someone who
achieved uh
nirvana Through The
Power Of The
practice in Their
former life even
before Lord budha
came to this planet
appeared on this
planet
and those those
those
ARS sitting around
you know especially
what we call R which
are the selfmade
ones Which doesn't
mean selfmade but
means in this life
They didn't have a
Direct teacher and
They were sitting
around and and they
heard this uh Voice
come from the sky
that says you know
Lord budha is
announcing Lord
about to come on the
planet you know
about show on theet
and some them are
attract ide someone
maybe not so I
didn't quite get
stra but they are
like going to do
some kind of
miracles to as a
as a precursor to
the budha appearing
on this planet so
they have this thing
called power over
the element of Fire
In Your Body This is
a high meditative
State where you can
actually uh
manipulate the
different elements
in your own body and
your own being so
they took the
elements of their
body and they
created themselves
on theot
CH and then they
could to  upir and all
these miracles  and
displ mirac then
finally they drop
down to the earth so
That's what uh
speech of the City
means dropping down
of the City means
That's why this
forest place is
called place Where
the City Spoke or
place the City fell
That's my take on
How translate
thate
iif I don't like
understand
mir so i'm sorry to
spend the time But I
don't feel
comfortable leaving
it Like That so um
so he says you know
we better get into
why people show
miracles at all you
know why why  people
show miracles at all
so uh he says
There's two ways to
show miracles uh you
know There are some
students that uh
will get into dharma
because they
understand that the
dharma is a sweet
thing and a true
thing and a
beneficial thing and
and those kind of
students You don't
have to do any
miracles or show
them weird things or
Like That they will
get into the dharma
on the basis of the
value of the dharma
because they
understand the
dharma is important
thing whether or not
handsome or look
good or  do miracles
or anything else but
there are other
kinds of  students
who need something
special you know
which is unrelated
to dharma but it
attracts them into
dharma so for those
kinds of students
There's this There's
this method of you
know go Fly in the
air you know If
you're a teacher
that has that
ability then if If
you read student
mind and you this
student is to
believe me unless I
show some kind of
amazing
and then If I show
some kind am even
The WR reas will and
then I can teach
them they can Go
ahead and show and
show miracles you
know So  That's
That's one kind of
reason why Somebody
might choose to go
up in the air and
fly around in the
air and That would
benefit the student
then There's a
second kind of
reason to show
miracles and he says
this is explained
in I chap could
think theth Chapter
where they discuss
different emanations
that the buddha
takes for the
benefit of other
people and WE
discuss them on
Australia and
California we
talking about
that the budha in
that Chapter
explains that the
buddha may undertake
different forms or
emanate in totally
different forms  So
that through that
emanation knowing
that the  minute they
see that emanation
that particular
student will get A
Certain important
spiritual concept
will Dawn on them
just by seeing that
emanation So it's
possible that a
teacher could emate
AS someone who could
Fly F around in the
sky and then the
student is just
sitting there
watching them and
then suddenly the
whole idea of
impermanence becomes
clear to them you
know It's no Direct
connection between
flying in the sky
and impermanence but
they've read the
student mind they
know that if the
student at such an
hour watches such a
guy flying around in
the sky  itl trigger
in them an idea that
they're very close
to like they have
some thought that
takes them on like
maybe they see like
a Bird and they
think Oh bird
you sometimes
the some great
spirit understanding
they will emate that
thing in order to
push them over into
that understanding
even though that
doesn't to do with
teaching in Words so so
then I said But I
still Don't whether
those those before
Lord budha came down
som Like That coming
to
mir
The Reason Now we
get to now might
come into Your mind
the way  did lose mind
that it seems like
they  somehow don't
like that the bud
coming down heaven
to teach DH in Their
in Their country
right in Their place
and so That's why
they're like
shooting up in the
air
andac don't need you
here now you know we
can do it ourselves
like That's not the
point That's not why
they're doing that
they Go up in the
air and they Start
to show these
miracles and all
that AS sort of a a
warning light to
Lord buddha saying
look uh There are
lots of great uh
Masters in this  land
already bod our
Hearts uh covering
rasi uh We are uh
undertaking to help
the people of this
land and there are
other lands in the
in the world where
they don't have any
teachers at all and
the buddhism hasn't
spread at all
and just call They
are shooting up a
war to showd that
There are already
great buddh
teachings going on
in this land and you
May prefer to go to
a land where
Absolutely no
teaching going on
those PO they're out
of concern out of
love for the beings
in other places that
don't have such  good
teachings they are
choosing they are
trying to send a
message to Lord You
know You don't have
to come down here
necessarily There
are other places
around where they
don't have any good
teachers So it's not
out of some
competitiveness
they're actually out
of a love or concern
for the people in
other surrounding
lands They are
Sending a message to
Lord buddha that you
know You don't have to
come down right
now for example uh
losan chinen uh goes
to America and and
teaches there
because There's just
a big vacuum  there
and He could just
stay here and hang
around here and and
study here and stuff
Like That but
There's such a huge
vacuum over there
it's better he goes
over there and hangs
out here and uh
they're trying to
send a message to
Lord and do the same
thing like
Oh
Now You guys being
from the West may
think that flying in
the sky is not such
a big deal because
you have these guys
that get up on the
side mountains and
jump off with hand
gliders and they go
hanging you know
gliding around and
to you It may not
seem such a big deal
but just want to out
these kind
of
without are in the
sky There's a bit of
distinction to here
you might think not
such a big deal but
without the
equipment that's a
big
deal time
on
uh
uh in this quotation
now in the sura uh
It's said that the
buddha is turning
the first the wheel
the reason for
turning the first
wheel is to benefit
students who have
entered the way of
TE right Which means
yana like in
mahayana or hinana
uh he for the
benefit of those who
have entered the way
of the listeners
Okay and listeners
has a lot of
connotations in budd
philosophy and he
says says great
teachers of the past
have taken this
wording in two
different ways Okay
So when you say that
the buddha Turn the
first turn of the
wheel for the
benefit of those who
had entered the way
of the listeners
then you have to
interpret that in
two different ways
There are two
different ways that
This can be
interpreted in one
way It's taken to
meant the lower of
the three tracks
right we talk about
three tracks track
of the listeners
track of thee
selfmade buddhas
which are  nei
selfmade nor buddh
and then the third
track
sp whoer the first
lowest of trs and
they entered the Now
emph
tracker lowest of
the tracks That's
one way explaining
what it means we
that Lord budha the
first
theel exp is you
think anent there
were great
philosophical
schools right those are
like the schools
the Logic and percep
Theory schools which
are called
su by the way the
first one are called
then the sutr the
third school is mine
only and the fourth
school is middle way
uh two of those
schools the top  two
are mahana schools
the lower two are h
schol and some great
scholars said when
they bud
first theel to help
those of the
listener he was
refering to People
who philosophically
entered the
viewpoints of the
lower two schools so
That would mean the
schools the schools
and the su schools
so what he saying is
that you can
interpret either one
of those two ways
either AS someone
Who's on to a
listener track among
the three tracks AS
aev
sch I don't
know or
um
to make a special
point that What
about to talk about
is not  relev to what
we talking about
right now
take
mind later so you
know I'm going to
throw in something
That's not directly
relevant to what
We're talking about
now but I want I
felt like itd be
good to talk about
it now so Excuse the
interruption uh he
says actually You
can take those three
tracks right uh the
listener track
selfmade buddha
track and the mahana
track and he says
really It's It's
that the lower
two tied together
and the upper one is
here so this is aana
track the top one is
aana track and these
two these two other
what we callet the
lower or hinana and
he says you know I
become aware of the
fact There are
people in burma
Thailand other
countries which are
followers of this
that Don't
appreciate being
called lower track
lower way which is
hinayana and There's
another word He's
heard which is
terada Which he
thinks maybe That
would be a nice word
to use since it
might offend them if
we talk about you
know translate to
tibetan directly
which is lower so
Let's talk about
terana so  these two
lower tracks are
terana and then this
track here isana but
If you take it in
terms of the four
philosophical
systems of ancient
india then you've
got abida the Logic
and perceptual
Theory sutr right
school and then
youve got min only
you've got middle
way school out of
those It's these two
ler ones Which We
Could describe
AS terab those are what
we call ter so
out of the three
tracks the lower two
ter out of the four
schools
So In among all  the
teachings of the
buddha we can divide
them into and terana
Right So we can
divide them into and
again he says in
Tibet the word comes
high way and lower
way you know so actually I mean so
actually It's
Yeah you could say
mahayana and lower
way right The Great
way and the lower
way Right So all div
into that now he
done A of reading
about kind
of lik out I
back i
bally so clear and
I've been reading a
lot about my whole
life been Into My
whole life How do
you make the real
distin
TE
matter but it seems
to be a very so I
want to talk about
it now how do you
draw between this is
teaching of the
buddha Which belongs
to mahana this is a
teaching the buddha
Which belongs to
terana and he says
really Haven we
presented two
different methods of
dividing it Haven we
one is by the three
tracks you know Are
you a person on
theana track or Are
you a person on one
of the of the ter
tracks and according
to the person that
we character the d t
to them AS being
mahana hinana so if
the  disciples are
what we call We can
call that teaching
if the teaching was
designed for
mahayana disciples
then we can call
that a mahayana
teaching if the
teaching was
designed or spoken
for hinana disciples
or ter disciples
then we can
characterize that
teaching AS ter or
hin teachings so are
we going to make
that distinction
based on whether
those students
belong to the lower
two of the three trs
or Are we going to
make distin based on
meaning are they
on a path or not
right or Are we
going  to make that
distinction based on
whether they belong
to the lower two
philosophical
schools in Their way
of thinking right
whether their way of
thinking the way of
believers or their
own tenants are
those of the lower
two philosophical
schools or the
higher tos We have
two choices here
right We can either
say this is if a
teaching was spoken
for for them it
becomes a h teaching
We can say teaching
was spoken for them
becomes teaching and
after much study and
after much
textbooks and other
people montic
textbooks and even
though It's not too
clear in the
writings that we
generally are
dealing with.  with here in
monastery you know
but If you go out
and you read further
and you keep reading
other textbooks it
seems clear to me
that this is the one
you have to
use any teaching
Which was directed
or designed for
students Which
belong to the lower
two of the four
great philosophic
schs of
ind my own are not
be confused with
schools ofet had
students who got
confused with those
but the schools of
ancient india that
those were
spoken for the
schools or for the
su schools uh those are are
spoken for
those become ter
teachings  If It was
t  for the benefit of
people whose
philosophical
thinking matches
that anybody in the
lower two
philosophical
schools that becomes
a ter teaching And
for those in the two
high schs becom mah
teaching And how we
draw the distin in
mind
lived different
routes and Can you
want you know
take
think
page
27 line 5 we going
get into the content
the First theel we
got go back to sura
and Here we go and
mentions mean
theuth
TR
naer
point
here in
world
we on this world
that we in here in
this world No one be
man god  has ever
come to this
particular planet
And spoken clearly
what it is what
those things are
that we are supposed
to follow And what
those things are
Which We are
supposed to not
follow or that we
are supposed to give
up and that is the
subject matter of
the four are truth
So In this world
only the incredible
extraordinary Lord
buddha is the one
who came and inion
clear out for us
What was we should
be doing And what
was we shouldn't be
doing we should in
particular
isd
lete
here me the
first of the
expressions isip LA
is the same LA as  in
lama meaning higher
one lama the literal
meaning of lama
means higher one and
so LA means above in
tibetan like kong in
tibetan means above
so LA NA chipa chipa
means To be or to
exist or to be
positioned above so
LA NA chipa means
that Which does have
something above It
something better
than it and the
point Here is that
there the there
EL there EL
isdel so says don't
think it's something
physical ok uh first
wheels down here 13
wheels up there 1
wheels  sitting on
top of the first not
like that
philosophically
speaking the third
the wheel is
philosophically
higher than the
first the wheel and
and that's why and I
think S in second
theel but mainly
first theel
actually be also so
There is theel which
is phos stand
thean Which means english
think
I think with open
and opening here
means Which means
occasion in tibetan
can be explained as
an opening for an
opponent to come and
Strike you you see
what I mean so he
says if if from the
mind only point of
View You're The  kind
of person who takes
the first turning of
theel to be literal
If you say that the
bud did mean uh what
He said in the first
the wheel you are
leaving yourself
Open you are leaving
an opening for
another person for
deb to come
philosophically you
You know You know
wrong on this point point
point you know
soip means There is
an opening leaving
yourself Open so so
far We have two
characters there high
and there is
opening here the
word occ means
chance means
Open are
chity
toic
mistakes means
opportunity
out
f
fin
think just Go ahead
and say Oh yeah  yeah
budha said that
everything from your
physical body up to
the 37 elements of
enlightenment all of
those Don't exist by
def none of them
exist by definition
sorry exist by
definition right in
the first the wheel
he goes and says
they all exist by
definition so from
the mind only school
point of View right
If you don't go
through all those
different elements
from the physical
body up to right the
seven groupings
right up to the
37 elements of
enlightenment you go
And this does EX by
definition this
doesn't EX by
definition this  does
this doesn't  some
person goes through
uh carpet you kno  w
like and says Oh
everything the bud
said that everything
here EX by
definition
everything by
definition If you
are like a blank sry
blanket Okay If you
make some kind of
blanket statement
Like That then you
are you are creating
that becomes a point
of contention right
If you had gone
through and divided
said does by
definition right sch
right If You Went
and dived out It
would no longer be a
point of contention
but Since You didn't
go through and
divide the Mount
then different
people can come with
different ideas I
think this one is
like that I think.
this one exist by
definition Somebody
EL No I think this
one does No I don't
think that one does
I think this one
does and then you
get all these
different points of
contention you get
all this argument
coming because of
your blanket stat
the bud meant
everything He said
when He said
all me me me
Oh BOY this is hard
uh Now we talk about
a point of
contention Somebody
fighting with
Somebody else right
and and so There's
different ways of
identifying who It
is that you'd be
arguing with right
who are you you are
min  only school
don't forget that
Okay you're in a
minority school suit
and uh You're going
to fight with
Somebody about the
meaning of the first
tur of the wheel in
the first turn of
the wheel Lord
buddha said that
everything from your
physical body up to
the 37 parts of
enlightenment uh do
exist by definition
so Who is it that we
can have a fight
with if This is a
bone of contention
this is if the first
of the wheel can be
characterized by the
bh AS being uh you
know something that
we can contend over
well then Who is  it
That would be having
contention Right So
on one side We have the
we have the mind
only schol would be
the contend on one
side right and on
the other side we
have to have
Somebody who
believed that the
buddha was literal
when He said that
everything from
physical your
physical body up to
the 37 parts of
enlightenment exist
by definition and
there are two great
ideas two great
schools have formed
about Who is it
among for example
the four
philosophical
schools That would
say that everything
in the in the in the
world exists by
definition just AS
buddha said it  and
and ges  says well on
the one side uh in
our little community
you have the Sarah J
textbooks ok in the
Sarah j textbooks
they say
that It's the lower
two schools right
thea and the school
two right who the
fighter Who's the
one contender number
three right this is
the mind only school
so the school is
going to have to be
saying the first of
the wheel is
something is a is
a point of
contention to have
contention you have
to have two
contending parties
Right So one
contending party is
going to be third
school which is the
school who are they
contending with and
Who is ever come the
bud was speaking
lally when He said
exed by defin so of
who in the ler two
schools is saying
that everything EX
by definition and in
the ser textbooks
they
say The People who
are saying that
everything exists by
definition are these
ler two schools They
are the school and
the sut school and
they do believe that
every exis by
definition
buts come along and
say you know these
lower two schools
Don't really believe
that everything
exists by definition
they only believe
that unchanging
things exist by
definition  Okay and
that Changing things
Don’t  exist by
definition Don't
Forget Don't confuse
what the min only
school says those
three groups and
Which of the three
groups exist by
definition if we
just restrict
ourselves to the
lower two schools
the says the ser
textbook says uh
There are people in
here they accept
that that unchanging
things exist by
definition and
Changing things
Don't exist by
definition but still
They are the people
that the mind school
is contending with
when you call the
first Turn the wheel
point of contention
Now g says I'm a ser
monk Oh but the he
also says that  the
amdo textbook seem
to tend to seem to side
towards the ser sign
Okay so the
textbooks out the
books out now he
says Now You know by
affiliation I'm A
ser monk and i and
when they ring that
when they when they
Hit The ser gong I
have to go you see I
mean I belong to sar
But I have to admit
that the S
explanation right
here makes a little
more Sense because
really If you think
about it We are
supposed to be
contending with
someone who takes
the first turning of
the wheel literally
and in the first tur
of the wheel  the
buddha  has says all
these things whether
they be Changing or
unchanging uh do
exist by definition
so You're going to have to
describe the
opponent in the
contender AS being
someone who accepts
that everything
exists by definition
because they have
someone who
ages hold bud was L
He said all those
things def so I
think on this point
despite my
affiliation I kind
have to say that
maybe they're right
on this point I kind
toward their
interpretation at
this
point Yeah I have
that
mif
that sch
inook presentation
believe that
unchanging things by
CH
things
got
I made a  big
advertisement about
me taking the taking
up the ser position
at this point th
when they rang
the gong for
assembly And for
lunch you know they
might kick me out so
i'm not making a big
advertisement
about they might
Tell me don't
come
appre
advertising just
King
we
don't
sch people
scho scho or not you
accept that people
in the ler two
schools make a
distinction between
some things existing
by definition and
other things not
existing by
definition It's not
really the point the
point is that we
have a bone of
contention We  have a
point of  contention
and that There are
going to be two
contenders here on
one side We have
the
back can
back
m expr remember be
exprs second first
is exactly the same
does have something
better does have
something above it
and again exactly
the same as in the
firstd
second where He said
that every existing
object exists by
definition it
doesn't exist by
definition no
existing object
exists by definition
if just on a blanket
basis you accept
that then you are
leaving yourself an
opening for whom for
the mind only school
to come and attack
you philosophically
and say you're wrong
you know  something's
wrong here so anyone
uh That's the
meaning uh the same
meaning with the
second turn of the
wheel AS with the
first tur the wheel
that you are leaving
yourself open for
for an attack for
critic
andd one is easy We
can character the
second the AS being
That was spen figura
because it's not
what it means ler
not to be taken on
face value not to be
taken as as what the
word says and
because of that
we can apply the
third
character
of you have to have
some kind of
disagreement between
two parties Who  are
the two parties here
on one hand  you have
the third sch which
is the mind only
school and then on
the other hand you
have Somebody who
saying that the
buddha was
literally the buddha
meant what He said
when He said that
every EX I'm sorry
that nothing in the
universe has any
existence by
definition Okay so
Who is it that
believes the bud was
being lal When The
bud Lord bud said
There's nothing
EX by That's thee
sch of the MID
way So that
upper of the school
that believes that
bud
being nothing that ine  E
section so make sure
we got off that  we
finished before this
thing went off and
that's why I'm about
to announce you my
one English word
that I know which is
I'm
sorry
think still some
point talk about
with second theel
and he there ating
what
weet point From
which you begin or
starting so said
There's going to be
five separate
sections to the
starting Where is it
from Where we take
froms he says Don't
down going back
back I want you
to be Don't start on
new paper right I'm
still back on the we
still have a few
pieces left from  the
second of the wheel
So don't forget
Don't go on Okay go
back up to where you
made your Mark for
the second turn of
the wheel we are
still polishing off
a few last points on
the second of the
wheel So don't
forget to go up to
the second wheel
where we left Off
You know talking
about the secondary wheel five what we call starting off points points
From which
We can take off bas Which where take we before Nature to Trans
of the
wheel or what we
Call the middle turn
of the  wheel we have
to we have to decide
Which disciples was
it that this
teaching was spoken
for you know who was
it that the middle
turning of the wheel
was designed for and
here in the text It
says for those who
had entered the
greater way right
for those who have
entered the path of
the greater way so
says again You can
divide it into these
two ways of
describing who
does he mean when he
says a person has
entered in greater
way is he talking
about a person who
in the highest of
school number school
number scho mind
school midle school
is that What it is
to be a person whoer
the greater way or
is it the person
Who's in the top of
the three tracks and
he says you know in
my idea again uh If
you're faced with
this Choice I have
to go with the top
two of the four
schools what the
buddha means when
the buddha says that
speaking the
second for those
whoer he talking
sch sch
people Now they're
identifying the
primary subject
matter remember that
the primary subject
matter mentioned
here for the first
the will was the
four truth and Now
the primary subject
matter for the
second  tur of the
wheel is  emptiness
AS understood by the
mind school Right So
It's going to be
emptiness for them
It's emptiness AS
they understand it
as the min school
understands it
Yeah
we get how we
established what it
was the buddha
really had in mind
when he t the second
of the wheel Because
it was those three
groups and it was
establishing the
meaning of totality
or emptiness by
examining the kind
of construct that
didn't exist with
regard to A Certain
Changing thing and
that's How in this
school we got to
what the  buddha
really had in mind
when he talked about
emptiness and So we
have to say
emptiness AS
understood by the
school we get to
this point
for
assembly prayers
assem who right now
is sch so If You Go
sticking
in idea of ​​emptiness
in when We're having
morning prayer of
just People who are
m only then you know
you're going to get
in Trouble so Once
youve entered into
the assembly the
monastic assembly
the mind only school
as a mind only
person you can't go
raising emptiness
according to the
middle
school just King you
know I guess  real
Nana
so wants to make
Sure that you're not
mixing up your notes
we through one set
of For the First
theel we went
another set of four
for the second Turn
the wheel you might
have start adding
stuff like a third
Turn the wheel or
something because he
already introduced
the 13 of the wheel
because he already
cut the borders
the boundaries of
the third turn wheel
He wants to make
Sure that you have
these notes in the
right place saying
that It was spen for
the benefit of
students who to the
greater way primary
subject
empel
mayel Something Like
make  that those two
character that spen
for the benefit of
those of the greater
way spen for benit
stud the greater way
and that prim matter
EMP Don't for that
up second
sayang second He
doesn't like to have
likes
fin
we there we there there we
there No
meant that to be
connected to the
second theel The
Reason he rushed to
the third theel AF
stupid thing was
going to go off he
says the L has three
RS and WE only
stepped on the
second and WE leave
it there get to the
rest later on today
tinytiny
all  time and you
couldn't get  squash
in there the guys be
out on the porch
baking in the sun
and and it was on
the Road
was
because afraid it
wouldn't get on the
tape so It was this
really weird classes
we used to have he
says you know Los
you were there you
know and then out of
concern for his
students Somebody
offered him this
house to build it
for him one of his
students who was in
England uh Who's the
ges at that center
and he offered to
build this house He
said Okay I'll do it
but just so my
students can have a
good place  to
have our teachings
inuse he didn't care
and he says Now it
seems like they
moved The Road
purposely
down to new
house
I think be in the
scripture when they
say you know your K
is going to follow
you You know You can
avo the K in one
form but if the
karma is still there
you can move and to
any you from the
coled no next my
house and I move my
house going to beise
next my
house
r s na na badashina